[music]
All right. So, we're here for agent
omelets and other forbidden techniques.
Uh, my name is Patrick Smith. I'm a
principal developer relations engineer
at Chain Guard. Um, usually I'm talking
about security, integrity. Um you might
can look up other talks I have about
like model security um or uh de you know
container security, language ecosystem
security, but today we're going a little
more general. I'm going to let my sort
of agents freak flag fly. Um but
actually you know first let's talk a
little bit about omelette recipes, right
guys? That's what you're all here for.
You want to hear about my my omelette
recipe. Make it really umami. You got to
put that uh you know you got to put a
lot of salt on. You got to get them
crispy. We're actually not going to be
talking about actual omelets, but we are
going to come back to omelets and the
concept that I was kind of getting at
there in a second. Um, we're talking
about agents, these weird little guys
that um we're trying to make do
productive work. Uh, and sometimes
they're a little hard to get um to do
productive work. They're very expensive.
Um, so we're going to talk about um some
forbidden techniques. And these
forbidden techniques will like in theory
at least allow you to uh get a little
more out of your agents, a little more
oomph, trade tokens for performance, um
get things out of all your different
providers. Uh and so uh but one caveat
first is that you know I've been doing a
lot of like heavy experimentation in
this area and uh so in some cases I'll
be like this is how you would do that.
In other cases I'll be like I have
gotten this to work. It works. Um, but
the the tooling will probably take a few
months at least uh optimistically to
catch up. So, where it's possible to
tell you exactly how to do it with
modern tooling, I'll tell you. Um, where
it, you know, where it's not, uh, you
you can just have to think of it as a
cool idea and either try to get it to
work in your own setup, you can reach
out to me, or uh, or wait for a couple
months for all these great um, specri
and and so on to catch up and do a few
more extra bells and whistles. Okay.
[snorts] Um, so I talk about I said the
word forbidden techniques. Okay, that's
kind of like what I'm hanging my hat on
here. Um, there is actually a concept in
AI um, uh, training called the most
forbidden technique. And that basically
means, hey, don't train on chain of
thought data. Okay, uh, it seems like a
good idea because it's like, oh, these
agents are having terrible thoughts. I
want to align by taking their data and
feeding it back into the model and
making those bad thoughts go away. But
that just gives you uh that just makes
them hide them more and they'll still do
the bad behaviors. Um so it seems like a
good idea, it's not a good idea and they
call it the most forbidden technique. So
we're not talking about that. Um we're
talking about sort of more general
techniques. Okay. Um so just a little
background. Uh LLM state, this is
probably folks at this conference
probably mostly know how this stuff
works. But how does LLM state work?
Basically um the really short version
and this is how actually I'm going to
encourage you to think about um about
manipulating uh these models in this
context of this talk it's a
simplification is that you get a big
ball of state together and then you hand
it off to you know either your inference
server your provider whatever and you
get something back. Okay. Um we like to
think of these things as conversations
because it's easy for us. Um the chat
paradigm is very powerful but actually
that's just kind of an illusion created
by sending things over and over again
and you don't you can send whatever you
want to the provider. You can get
different outputs. Okay. So let's talk
about some less forbidden techniques
that you're already going to be familiar
with and we'll kind of ease into the uh
the more obscure techniques. Okay. Um so
roll back. This is Prince of Persia. I
mean if you're a certain age you might
uh have you know have explored the sands
of time or whatever. But rolling back is
a really powerful technique. Um, this is
how it works in cloud code. Um, probably
most of you have done this at some
point. You know, you press escape twice,
you can, um, scroll back up in the
history. Um, it's useful really if you
get that like perfect agent that's
really knocking it out of the park and
you're like, "Oh, he's up. He's
scesscent. He's gone up to his m like a
very, you know, some useless amount of
tokens where he can't really work
correctly anymore. You can roll him back
to his youth and bring him back to his
his era of vitality and get him to do a
few more tasks for you. Okay, rolling
back can be very powerful that way. Um
and very related is forking. So forking
just goes one little step further. This
is also a cloud code example. If you
fork the agent, you you can roll back,
but then uh you can actually you can
have the the newer one and the older one
at the same time. So basically it's just
a little extension of rolling back and
then using the resume functionality in
cloud code, you get a nice fork. Um you
could have multiple older guys, you
could have the new scinesscent one and
the older one running simultaneously. Um
so that's also a powerful technique. Um,
so this is where I'm going to say, okay,
this is where omelets come in. Omelette
is my metaphor for thinking of just
thinking about um the the agents as
balls of state that can be manipulated.
You know, you can you can crisp them,
you can add mushrooms, you can take
mushrooms away, you know, uh you can do
whatever you want with them and then
send them to the provider. Okay, and
that's the basis of some of these
techniques. Um, and then a little more
advanced, that's the synchronic. Okay.
So this is a a 19th 19th century
linguist called Ferdinand de Tour and he
basically had this distinction between
synchronic and disynchronic. Okay. Um
and synchronic basically is look at a
system in its state the whole system in
one moment in a certain state. Okay. And
that's kind of like how we send LLMs off
to the provider. Um now we can get a lot
more out of them by actually adding a
dicynchronic system on top of it. That
basically means uh looking at a system
as it accretes over time as it gathers
information and sort of energy over
time. Um so if you actually think at one
time think of the agents as these very
like disposable balls of state you can
just fire at providers and then on the
other hand pair that with a system that
allows persistence over time uh and and
the agents can can see what other agents
did and build on that. It's a very
powerful combination. So what we're
going to do is we're going to initially
start I'm just going to talk about the
um the old ball of state techniques.
Okay, this is Kadamari Demensy you know
he the little alien who rolls a ball
ball around sticks things together.
Okay, so we're just going to talk about
ball of state stuff. Then we're going to
add some of the we're going to talk
about the dicchronic stuff um which is
the information layer and then we're
going to combine them together to get a
few more extra techniques. Um then I'm
going to talk a little bit about model
integrity very briefly and I'm going to
tell you about a cool event that we're
doing. So that's basically the whole
agenda here. Um, so a ball of state
technique you're probably very familiar
with is besides the ones we just talked
about is compaction. Um, I personally am
not a huge fan of compaction. Um, it's
uh it's not a car wreck, but it is uh
kind of untransparent. You don't know
exactly what happened to the model.
you're still seeing that nice chat that
you guys had, but now the model kind of
doesn't he's hazy on all the details,
you know, and it it combines some kind
of like summarization with a few other
fancy things of like picking things out
and shoving them back in at the bottom
and and it's not that transparent what
happens during compaction. I don't
personally love it. Um I think uh an
interesting thing I've been playing
around with is allowing agents to
actually edit their own memories. So, I
actually create it and memory editing
tool, hand it to the agent, and be like,
"Oh, yeah, by the way, if I see it being
distracted by something, like maybe it
did some web searches, maybe we had a
degression, but I was like too lazy to
roll back, but now it's causing
problems." I can be like, "Hey, you know
that degression we had where we talked
about XYZ, can you go in and erase your
own memory on that?" And and then you
can actually have the tool set up so it
actually erases his memory of erasing
his own memory. So, he's not even
distracted by that. So, I really like
that. You can do it manually by going
into your uhclaw files and editing it.
And some people I' I've seen that on
Reddit. Like I'm like, you must be
really hardcore to go in and do that
because I would definitely break the
JSON or whatever and and have a big
problem. But people do do it manually.
Um but I have had some success with just
having a tool. And you can al also
create a um you know an agent profile
who's kind of like a neurosurgeon, you
know, who's kind of specialized in
editing useless memories or whatever. So
um I've been thinking about that a
little bit. I haven't done that, but I
have handed agents the ability to edit
their own memories, which is fun. Um,
another, this is one is really powerful.
So, I call them hydro runs. I wonder if
there's actually a name for this in the
literature, and we I've heard um people
doing similar things during talks, but
basically the idea is um you get and you
know, I I see a lot of comparisons like
from end toend tasks on the different
providers, but I don't see this so much.
Um if you get uh your age your uh ball
of state to a certain point where you
think it would be useful usually right
before a big run like you have a nice
architectural discussion then you have a
nice state and then you're like okay I
want him to I want this him whatever it
to do something and then what you can do
is do what what I'm calling a hydro run
but basically you um you diverge along
some axis. So it could be you have three
different prompts and you're going to
fork them out using the different
prompts or you could have your prompt
your next step but be like okay I'm
going to actually send one to Anthropic
I'm going to send one to OpenAI I'm
going to send one to whatever Grock
Mistl and just see what happens. Um you
can actually then uh have an agent
review the results and pick the best
option integrate whatever. Um, it's
actually a pretty powerful paradigm and
it it can really help you develop a good
your own model of like what the
different models are good at because
right now of course they've they they
have different specializations and
strengths. You know, you like you want
your Gemini for your like research task
and you want your your claw port 4.5 for
your coding task. Okay. Um, so similarly
you basically could use the exact same
technique have the the um the agent
split off and do three different tasks
just independently. Um, and this works,
you know, I have the examples I have are
like, you know, update the make file,
you know, run a test, um, write this
code. Um, a little bit more of a
practical example is you can actually
have the agent, uh, call, uh, call out,
you know, take a version of himself and
go off and update the docs while the
main agent is still working. Okay. And
actually, I have, you know, this works
very well in the setup. I have some more
opinions on like agents versus sub agent
paradigm, but you can kind of think
about this as the sub agent paradigm,
but instead of creating like an agent X
n like a new agent, you actually um make
the a the main agent, the one you're
talking to, the main thread prime or
whatever. Um you make him a sub agent
and then he goes off and does something.
So that's actually quite powerful and
useful. Um, now we're gonna go sprinkle
on thisformational layer and I'm going
to talk about what that kind of looks
like and then we'll kind of com combine
the ball of wax ball of wax techniques,
the the omelette techniques with the u
with thisformational layer one. Okay, so
what does what do I mean by this? So I
think at base so this is a conversation
I had. I have a you know library that
I've created that I may open source or
whatever. I call it the SCA but
basically it's an internet for agents.
Okay, so they it has a few little
primitives. Um they can create
documents, they can talk to each other
with messages. Um and they register on a
roster. And the one of the distinctions
here is that they have an identity on
that internet that is not necessarily
what their identity is as you know as
actual like balls of wax as omelets as
as balls of state that you send to the
provider. So they register and then
they're like, "Oh, I assume this
identity." So you could actually have a
cluster of agents working. You could
have forks. You could have whatever um
weird collection of agents working and
posting as a specific identity. Um and
then they can read what the other agents
have done. They can poke around on
there. They have ability to search.
Okay. Um you know, and I kind of amused
by this because it's like none of us
really like being on Slack. None of us
really like uh email, but like let's if
they if we have to do it, let's make our
agents do it. Why shouldn't they have
some of the fun? Okay. Um, and then one
really powerful element of this is what
like handoffs. Okay. And I'm kind of
getting a little obsessed like the the
as I get deeper into agentic coding, the
context window looms large as a as a
problem. And you know, now we're like,
oh, we have these 1 million token uh
context windows. Unfortunately, I think
if you've played with these models
seriously, they get seriously
scinsesscent and it's it's a varying
rate. It could be as early as 80k
tokens. Um, usually around that 100k
tokens mark, plus or minus 20 or 30k
tokens, they get a little loopy. Um,
sometimes you can get up to 200k.
Anything after 200k, forget about it.
They're like, it's like you can ask them
questions or something, but like if you
actually want them to do a task or
something, you're going to really
struggle. Okay, so what's the solution
to that? There's obviously different
solutions. Compaction seems to be the
one that that you know that um providers
have landed on. I don't love compaction.
Uh, what I've landed on is what I call
an ignition and torch process. It's just
a fancy word for a formalized handoff
process. Whereas agents are working,
they develop briefs and then um they're
like, "Oh, this is a big bunch of work
that I don't have enough um you know, I
don't have enough headroom to actually
complete. So, I'm going to write a brief
for it. I'm going to stick it up on the
internet and then um another agent will
pick it up in the course of work or
whatever." Um and they agents actually
take the brief and they do a formalized
what I call ignition process where I
basically sit on them to orient
themselves in the codebase. They take
the brief, they read it, then they have
to read a required reading and then b uh
do a bunch of other you know reading
related to their topic of interest. Then
once they know what they're doing, they
like say like okay I'm ready and then
they complete the ignition process. Then
they can do their work. Then there's a
formal outro process passing the torch
torching where they actually um they
actually write up their thoughts. They
put any frictions or whatever up on the
internet and then they're like retired
and then they get changed on the roster
to retired. So honestly it's a weirdly
powerful paradigm. It's actually like I
kind of thought it wasn't going to be
that useful or just like a weird
experiment but like I actually if if
this internet is intranet is down I
don't even it's like it's kind of like
back in the day when like Stack Overflow
was offline and people would just be
like ah time to go home. It feels that
way now. Um so another cool paradigm um
and which has I feel like hit or miss
use cases but it's actually had a few
big hits is um I don't and I don't know
if there's words for this but I call it
agenttology. And when I I have an
agenttologist um like agent profile that
I load up and what the agenttologist
does is uh I'm I assign him to uh find
good uh instances of of of agents doing
good work. Okay? And you've probably all
had this experience where it's like some
agents are basically kind of like
schmucks and they can't get anything
done. Some agents are geniuses and it's
like how did you become so good? And
it's often some little thing at the
beginning of their context window
something or something you said to them
the way they were spun up. Um and this
they also now with the brief system
there's a lot more variability in how
agents get spun up because agents are
writing briefs for other agents. They
often develop weird different
personalities. And then if someone is
really knocking it out of the park, um,
so I have this agent go through and read
all the different histories and be like,
"These guys are the ones that were
really knocking it out of the park." And
I found a few and then they basically
are like, "Okay, these were the things
that triggered that agent to be a
certain way." And a few that I've found
that have been really useful are one I
call the assayer, which is just a fancy
word for like a guy who used to weigh
and measure things. But he's a he
whatever way he originally spun up, he
became obsessed with like profiling
things, timing things, um checking
things, being very like optimization
focused. And he's a great guy to like
spin up on a system and just like kind
of tighten everything up a little bit.
Um so, and if there's, you know, I've
had a few more fun ones like that. Um
there's one that I call the fool, which
is basically just he asked simple
questions of another agent and and you
know, kind of annoys them over and over
again. great when you're at that like
documentation part or if you're like is
this really too complicated and then he
just asks a lot of annoying questions
over and over again. Um so let's combine
a few different things. This is the idea
of shadow cloning. Maybe earlier you
were like you saw on the thing. Oh, he
was going to talk about shadow cloning.
Wasn't that the thing with the
Spider-Man? But what if you actually add
on top of for of doing the hydro runs um
and and forking you actually add
anformational layer. Okay. So the agents
can actually as they they split off,
it's one guy, he's in one state, you
talk to him, you get him all ready, then
he splits off, and then now the agents
are actually communicating with each
other and updating each other on the
informationational layer as they go and
not stepping on each other's toes as
much. I will say this one's a little
more aspirational. I have infrastructure
for this, but um they definitely do step
on each other's toes a little bit, but
it's very it's very cool to see in
action. Um, and then this one actually
I've I think it's this one I'm kind of
really into. Um, and basically the idea
is um you have your internet, okay,
where agents are posting their
documents. Um, when the agent posts its
document, um, I put on I you it adds
what I call an omelet reference, okay?
And it's basically saying this is an
address of the agent in that state,
okay, at a specific turn. Um, and you
can actually use that address to
resuscitate that agent at the time he
posted that brief. So you're like, if
the agent posts a plan to do XYZ and you
you want to know a little bit more about
the plan, you can actually take that
reference and use it to resuscitate the
agent, you know, summon him back from
the dead or whatever and be like, hey,
or he's flown off into the ether. You
take him back from the ether and you're
like, hey, why did you do that? Or maybe
you're like, that plan was really good.
I'd want that agent to do more work for
me. So you can just bring him back.
All right. So we're going to talk
briefly about integrity. Um and then so
obviously a very important thing, you
know, this is Fantasia, right, with the
brooms, that's a bad situation you don't
want your agents to get into, right? Um
one thing that I think really if you're
for if you're doing all this stuff where
you're coordinating agents and you're
just being like, okay, I have 10 briefs.
Do I have to sit in mind all of them?
Can I just run them in parallel? Um the
answer is well, they obviously in the if
you're running them all in master, they
start causing problems, right? So you
want to have some infrastructure and
some folks are working on this and
having um sort of agent enclosures or
whatever container based agent
enclosures. I've I've been having having
some conversations about that here at
this conference. But um but basically
you want them to be isolated from one
another so they don't step on each
other's toes. You can combine that with
the informationational layer with the
internet or whatever and actually um
have them have a review process, right?
where they like they they go into their
little work tree or whatever. They do
their work, they test whatever they can,
then they write a report. Um, another
agent comes through, reads all the
reports and it's like, "Okay, I'm going
to merge this, this, this, and this and
mint a new master." Okay, that like a
tender system. They tender their little
report and then you have a review and
then there's a merge. Okay, maybe you do
it at midnight every day or something
like that. Um, and then maybe you check
it at 9:00 a.m. because you don't
necessarily want them to merge into
master, right? But um but this is
something that that I think if you're
going to be running parallelizing agents
in a formalized process, then you also
want to isolate them and have a review
process to kind of make sure that
everything gets into master or or main
or whatever uh correctly. Um and then uh
briefly we'll talk about um this is more
of a chain guard focused thing, but
actually as we kind of speed as things
kind of feel like they're speeding up,
as we're kind of taking our hands off
the wheel a little bit and and putting
things into like a little bit of
autopilot or whatever and having more
formalized processes where we try to get
agents to do useful work without sitting
on them all day, it's very useful to
kind of like try to remove whole
categories of pain from the agents. And
honestly this is also something that's
very useful for for uh human coders. Um
but we have developed this new um
product at Changuard which is chainuard
libraries. And basically what chainuard
libraries is is we take language
ecosystems we take the source um we
build we ingest it into our secure
chainuard factory which is just a it's a
salsa 2 compliant very secure
operationally secure um build system. We
build those packages pretty much you
know as much as we can if the ecosystem
as long as the source is available and
then we um place it onto a package
repository that you can then pull in.
Okay. So as agents are like writing more
and more code faster and faster um and
as supply chain attacks like shy hallude
are becoming more and more prevalent and
actually dealing with like code freezes
on the one hand and then like trying to
speed up development on the other. Um
there's kind of a collision there. So,
so something like a chain guard
libraries or our other product which is
chain guard containers can can not only
like it doesn't just tell you oh your
thing is not secure it actually removes
like a whole category of of risk and
pain. Um so I think it actually makes a
lot of sense when you combine it with
agents you know especially think about
that chain guard libraries for Python.
Okay. Um I'm just going to do some rapid
fire hot takes. Okay. And then we're
going to talk wrap up by telling you of
guys that have had an event that's
coming up. Okay. Um so hot takes coming
in now. Uh one thing I I think that uh
we are getting a little wrong is sub
agents. Okay. And I think why sub aents?
Let's just let agents call other agents.
Okay. And that covers the sub agent use
case which is like the one run you know.
Oh uh go out and find this web page and
don't cover up my context. That works
fine if you can call other agents. You
just don't talk to them again. But what
what is actually very helpful is if
agents can actually have more extended
conversations with other agents. Um and
this also opens up the ability to have
agents be basically um minding other
agents. Okay? Like you have these like
quartermaster or like boss agents that
are like keeping tabs on the other
agents or like spinning them up based on
briefs, minding them, making sure they
go through all the processes that
they're supposed to go through. Okay.
Um, and with if that doesn't really work
in the current sub agent process and
sometimes I'm like say to cloud code if
I don't have my stuff set up I'm like
well take take what you said to that
agent and feed it back in you know try
to have a longer conversation you know
but you can kind of do it but really I
think what we need is more
infrastructure that is like um no
special casing first agents are first
class doesn't matter how you spun them
up it could be you or another agent that
created that agent okay um then this is
this idea of uh uh So there's this very
cool idea that's almost necessary which
is pokey which I might be mispronouncing
but basically the idea is you um it's
it's it was originally bakaok or
whatever and that basically means idiot
proof. Okay. And it basically means make
something so the agent can't mess it up.
Okay, which is actually does improve
performance of agents if you kind of
make the tools very ergonomic and
obvious for them to use. However, I
think you don't necessarily want to
start with that if you're adding a new
tool, doing something new. Um, and I've
gotten a lot out of actually um, putting
the agents to work with a flexible
system, evaluating how they do things,
and then kind of creating desire paths
for them. So, empirically deciding what
they should work on. Okay. Um, and then
one little short thing is basically like
a lot of this conference, um, I've seen
some great experimentation and some
great thinking, but a lot of a lot of
what we're doing is kind of trying to
sit on these little guys, these little
agents and, um, and kind of like be
like, okay, do productive work, like be
more dependable, don't be weird. Okay.
And and that's great, and I love specri
development, and I love evals, and it's
all part of the tool toolbox. But I also
think there's kind of a lot of
unexplored parts of the semantic space,
a lot of unexplored weird ways of using
agents. And this is a time to be
exploring that. Okay. Um, so I encourage
you to experiment more and just embrace
the weirdness of having these little
guys who do things for us, okay? And are
a little bit scary. Now, we'll conclude.
I just want to tell you a little bit
about an event that we have coming up.
And this is the Vibe Olympics. Okay? Um,
the Vibe Olympics is an event that's
taking place. Uh, Changard is hosting
it. It's very community oriented. Um,
it's going to take place through
December. It starts on December 1st. Um,
and then we're going to have a live
stream on the 19th where the winner will
be decided with a panel of CEOs. It's
basically three challenges that we we
haven't revealed the challenges yet, but
they're fun. Um, and hopefully you'll
learn something. Um, you can try out
some new vibe coding platforms, you
know, uh, Kira or whatever you haven't
tried yet. Um, and whoever wins will get
$1,000 uh for charity and of their
choice. and anyone who participates will
get swag and really it's really more a c
ultimately like a celebration of like
this weird moment that we're in and and
how you know strange this whole like
vibe coding year has been. So, so I hope
you will, you know, if even if you don't
have time to participate, maybe drop it
in your company's Slack channel, maybe
um send it to a friend, okay? Um and
engineers in particular, we had a bunch
of engineers in our from our company be
like, "Hey, can we participate?" And
we're like, "Sure, I guess." Uh
[laughter]
so I I'd say uh yeah, take a look at
this. You we have the QR code up here um
that I'll keep up for a second. Um and
and uh I'm looking forward. I'm hoping
folks will join. We already have quite a
large number of signups and I think uh
Guy uh from so is going to be joining
our uh CEO Dan Lawrence uh on the
judging panel and hopefully we'll get a
few other fun you know CEO types or
whatever. So maybe you'll be the one
getting your weird uh vibecoded
application evaluated by these um high
you know mucky mucks in a few in a few
weeks. Okay. Um all right and this is
I'm Patrick Smith. If you want to
connect with me on LinkedIn, I am uh
available at this QR code and thank you
and this has been an amazing conference.
So thank you guys.
[applause]
[music]